James MacKillop Collection
Onondaga Community College
James MacKillop Collection
1962 - 2004
The James MacKillop collection contains material donated to the Onondaga Community College archives by English Professor James MacKillop. Material includes Master's thesis and doctoral dissertation, manuscripts for books written or edited by James MacKillop and correspondence with fellow writers.
5.2 linear feet
Onondaga Community College; mackillop, james
4585 W Seneca Turnpike Syracuse, NY 13215
MacKillop, James; correspondence; Onondaga Community College; manuscripts (documents); floppy disks; doctoral dissertations; masters theses; postcards; professors (teachers); authors; Mythology, celtic; Film criticism; Irish literature 20th century History and criticism
This collection is open to researchers without restriction.
Dr. James MacKillop was a professor of English at Onondaga Community College from 1967 to 1999. As a professional writer for over thirty years, MacKillop published books and articles about Celtic mythology and Irish Literature. His most well-known titles are the "Dictionary of Celtic Mythology" (1998), and "Myths & Legends of the Celts" (2005). MacKillop received a PhD in English Literature from Syracuse University. He is currently the editor of the Irish Series at Syracuse University Press.
The collection comprises archival materials relating to the professional career of James MacKillop. The materials are arranged as given by the author. The main categories of the collection manuscripts and correspondence relating to "Envisioning Ireland" anthology, "Dictionary of Celtic Mythology" manuscripts, "Irish Literature: A Reader" manuscripts, series: "The Myth of Finn MacCool in the English Literature: A Study of a Celtic Archetype in the Works of James MacPherson, Flann O'Brien, James Joyce and Others" by James MacKillop (Ph.D dissertation), "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" manuscripts, and MacKillop's Master's Thesis on T.E. Hulme.
Series 1: "Envisioning Ireland: Essays on Irish Cinema" papers. This series includes material related to the book, "Envisioning Ireland: Essays on Irish Cinema" edited by James MacKillop. Materials include manuscripts and correspondence with contributing writers to the book. Correspondence, arranged by MacKillop, is alphabetical by author's last name.
Series 2: "Dictionary of Celtic Mythology" papers. This series includes material related to the book, "Dictionary of Celtic Mythology." Material includes manuscripts and newspaper clipping.
Series 3: "Irish Literature: A Reader" papers. This series contains material related to, "Irish Literature: A reader" written by James MacKillop and Maureen O'Rourke. Contains manuscript and galley proof.
Series 4: "The Myth of Finn MacCool in the English Literature: A Study of a Celtic Archetype in the Works of James MacPherson, Flann O'Brien, James Joyce and Others." This series contain's a copy of MacKillop's PhD dissertation.
Series 5: "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" papers. This series contains material related to the book, "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop. Materials included manuscripts and page proofs.
Series 6: Master's Thesis on T.E. Hume. This series contains a copy of James MacKillop's Master's thesis.
- "Envisioning Ireland: Essays on Irish Cinema" by James MacKillop (Editor), 1992 - 1999; Typed manuscript for "Envisioning Ireland: Essays on Irish Cinema," edited by James MacKillop. 418 pages. Correspondence with authors of essays for the book included.
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" Publication, 1997 - 1998; Typed sheets to authors of content for "Envisioning Ireland" regarding publication sent by James MacKillop. Includes release for publication sheets. (Box MAC-10)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Margot Gayle Backus, 1995 - 1997; Typed copies, with revisions, of "Revising Resistance: In the Name of the Father as Postcolonial Paternal Melodrama" by Margot Gayle Backus. Includes floppy disk, bibliography and note to James MacKillop. (Box MAC-10)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Susan M. Bernardo, 1993 - 1995; Typed letters from Susan M. Bernardo to James MacKillop regarding "Veiling the Gaze in the The Crying Game: Through a Glass Darkly," an essay to appear in "Envisioning Ireland." Includes manuscript of "Veiling the Gaze" and 2 floppy disks. (Box MAC-10)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Douglas Brode, 1993 - 1997; Correspondence regarding "Man's Mythic Journey and the Female Principle in My Left Foot," essay by Douglas Brode for "Envisioning Ireland" book. Includes typed manuscript of essay, floppy disk, and typed letter by James MacKillop to Brode with editorial comments. (Box MAC-10)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Marina Burke, 1993 - 1995; Typed letters from Marina Burke to James Burke regarding "Neil Jordan's the Crying Game in the Context of Issues of Race and Transexuality in the Film." Includes typed manuscript of the essay for "Envisioning Ireland." (Box MAC-10)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Jennifer Cornell, 1995; Typed letters regarding essay, "'Different Countries, Different Worlds': The Representation of Northern Ireland in Stewart Parker's 'Lost Belongings,'" for "Envisioning Ireland" book. Includes essay manuscript and floppy disk. (Box MAC-10)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" Ian Crump, 1993; Typed letter from Ian Crump regarding essay under consideration for "Envisioning Ireland" book. Includes typed manuscripts for essay, "Male Bonding: O'Connor, Behan, and Jordan." (Box MAC-10)
  - Photocopy of "Seamus and Sinead: From 'Limbo' to Saturday Night Live by way of Hush-a-Bye Baby" by Elizabeth Cullingford, 1992 - 1998; Photocopy of essay titled, "Photocopy of "Seamus and Sinead: From 'Limbo' to Saturday Night Live by way of Hush-a-Bye Baby" by Elizabeth Cullingford (Box MAC-10)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Marianne Eismann, 1994 - 1995; Letters to James MacKillop regarding essay, "Secret Sharers: Forming Community in Neil Jordan's 'The Crying Game.'" Includes manuscripts for essay and floppy disks. (Box MAC-10)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Helen Emmitt, 1993 - 1994; Letters regarding essay, "'It's Only a Piece of Meat': Gender and Signification in 'The Crying Game'" for inclusion in "Envisioning Ireland" book. Includes manuscripts and floppy disk. (Box MAC-10)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with University of Florida Press, 1992 - 1994; Letters to James MacKillop from University of Florida Press regarding "Envisioning Ireland" book. Includes formatting guidelines for authors for publication. (Box MAC-10)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland", 1994 - 1996; Various correspondence relating to "Envisioning Ireland" book. Includes postcard from contributing writer, Jennifer Cornell, letters from University Press of Florida, and typed letters to book contributors from James MacKillop. (Box MAC-10)
  - Postcard and Manuscript from Leonard Frey to James MacKillop, 1993 (Box MAC-10)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with John Hill, 1995; Typed letter to James MacKillop with typed manuscript for essay, "'The Past is Always There in the Present:' Fools of Fortune and the Heritage Film." (Box MAC-11)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Kerstin Ketteman, 1993 - 1995; Letters regarding manuscript for "Envisioning Ireland" book. Manuscript titled "Cinematic Images of Irish Male Brutality and the Semiotics of Landscape in 'The Field' and 'Hear My Song.'" Floppy disk included. (Box MAC-11)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Anthony Kirby, 1993 - 1996; Typed and hand-written letters between Anthony Kirby and James MacKillop regarding "A Filmography if Irish and Irish-Related Feature Films" by Kirby. (Box MAC-11)
  - Manuscripts of Anthony Kirby's Essay for "Envisioning Ireland", 1996; Copies of Anthony Kirby's "Selected Filmography of Irish & Irish-Related Feature Films." (Box MAC-11)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Jim Loter, 1995; Letter from Jim Loter regarding paper for "Envisioning Ireland." Includes first page of paper, footnotes, and floppy disk. (Box MAC-11)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Kathleen McCracken, 1992 - 1996; Typed and hand-written letters from Kathleen McCracken regarding essay for "Envisioning Ireland" book. Various versions of the manuscript for the essay included. (Box MAC-11)
  - Manuscript for"Envisioning Ireland" by Martin McLoone, 1993 - 1996; Typed manuscript titled, "'December Bride:' A Landscape Peopled Differently" by Martin McLoone for "Envisioning Ireland" book. (Box MAC-11)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Brian McIlroy, 1992 - 1997; Typed letters and manuscripts from Brian McIlroy to James MacKillop. Several versions of "The Feminist Historical and Political Documentary Reconsidered: Anne Crilly's 'Mother Ireland.'" (Box MAC-11)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Moylan C. Mills, 1992; Typed letters and manuscripts regarding essay for "Envisioning Ireland." Essay titled "Huston and Joyce: Bringing 'The Dead' to the Screen. Floppy disk included. (Box MAC-11)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Maria Pramaggiore, 1994 - 1998; Letters regarding essay for "Envisioning Ireland." Several versions of essay, titled, "'I Kinda Liked You as a Girl': The 'Nature' of Terrorism, Sexual Politics and Postcolonial Queens in Neil Jordan's 'The Crying Game,'" included. Floppy disk included. (Box MAC-11)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Lori Rogers, 1992 - 1993; Letters and correspondence regarding essay titled, "'That's Everybody's Tune': Images of Celticism in Neil Jordan's 'Angel." Several versions of essay manuscript included. (Box MAC-11)
  - Sanford Sternlcht's Manuscript for "Envisioning Ireland" Book, 1992 - 1996; Three copies of manuscript of essay titled, "Synge on Film: Two Playboys." (Box MAC-11)
  - Gail Sweeney Manuscript for Envisioning Ireland, 1993; Manuscript for "Envisioning Ireland" titled "'A Good Stick to Beat the Lovely Lady': Violence and Equality in John Ford's 'The Quiet Man.'" (Box MAC-11)
  - Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland" with Kathy Gallagher Winarski, 1993 - 1995; Letters to James MacKillop regarding "Envisioning Ireland" essay. Includes copies of manuscript for the book. Includes floppy disk. Essay is titled "Neil Jordan's Miracle: From Fiction to Film." (Box MAC-11)
  - Manuscript for "The Quiet Man Speaks" by James MacKillop for "Envisioning Ireland" book., 1992 - 1995; Typed manuscript and photo-copied manuscript for "The Quiet Man Speaks" by James MacKillop. (Box MAC-11)
  - Footnotes Manuscript for "Envisioning Ireland", 1992 - 1998; Typed footnotes for "Envisioning Ireland" book. (Box MAC-11)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence Regarding "Envisioning Ireland", 1992 - 1993; Miscellaneous letters to James MacKillop regarding "Envisioning Ireland Book." (Box MAC-11)
  - "Envisioning Ireland: Essays on Irish Cinema" Manuscript by James MacKillop (Editor), February, 1998; Typed manuscript for "Envisioning Ireland: Essays on Irish Cinema," edited by James MacKillop. 418 pages. (Box MAC-06)
- "Dictionary of Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 1995 - 1998; Manuscripts and book blurb for Dictionary of Celtic Mythology
  - "Dictionary of Celtic Mythology" Part 1 Manuscript by James MacKillop, 1995 - 1998; Typed Manuscript of Part 1 of Dictionary of Celtic Mythology. (Box MAC-03)
  - "Dictionary of Celtic Mythology" Part 2 Manuscript by James MacKillop, 1995 - 1998; Part 2 of typed manuscript with hand-written comments and notations. 668 pages. (Box MAC-04)
  - "Dictionary of Celtic Mythology" Book Blurb Newspaper Clipping, March, 2001; Newspaper clipping from "Irish Echo" on "Dictionary of Celtic Mythology. Newspaper clipping is taped to white sheet of paper. 4 photo-copies of clipping included. (Box MAC-02)
  - "Dictionary of Celtic Mythology" Draft Manuscript by James MacKillop, 1999 - 2001; Typed manuscript with hand-written comments of "Dictionary of Celtic Mythology." Comments by Derick Thomson. (Box MAC-09)
  - "Dictionary of Celtic Mythology" Manuscript by James MacKillop, 1999 - 2001; Typed manuscript with handwritten notes of "Dictionary of Celtic Mythology." Comments by Ellis Evans. (Box MAC-09)
- "Irish Literature: A Reader" by James MacKillop & Maureen O'Rourke Murphy, 1987; Typed manuscript and galley proof with hand-written comments and notations.
  - "Irish Literature: A Reader" Manuscript by James MacKillop & Maureen O'Rourke Murphy, 1987; Typed manuscript of "Irish Literature: A Reader." 439 pages. (Box MAC-05)
  - "Irish Literature: A Reader" Galley Proof, 1987; Galley proof of "Irish Literature: A Reader." Typed manuscript with hand-written comments and notations. 475 plus pages. (Box MAC-05)
- Miscellaneous to James MacKillop, 1993 - 1998; Miscellaneous documents related to James MacKillop.
  - Gifford Lecture Previews Flyer, 2001; Flyers for Gifford Lecture Previews advertising James MacKillop's lecture, Fall 2001. (Box MAC-01)
  - First Annual Syracuse Stage Guild Tour to Stratford Festival, Ontario Information Packet, April, 2004; Printed papers regarding Syracuse Stage Guild trip to Stratford, Ontario. (Box MAC-02)
- "The Myth of Finn MacCool in the English Literature: A Study of a Celtic Archetype in the Works of James MacPherson, Flann O'Brien, James Joyce and Others" by James MacKillop (Ph.D dissertation), July, 1975; Typed dissertation for PhD in English for Syracuse University. 445 pages. (Box MAC-07)
- "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 2000 - 2001; Typed manuscripts, correspondence, and flyers relating to "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-01, MAC-02, MAC-08)
  - Introduction, "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" Manuscript by James MacKillop, 1998 - 2001; Introduction to "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" typed manuscript with hand-written comments. (Box MAC-01)
  - "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" Manuscript by James MacKillop, June 5, 2001; Manuscript for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" with editor's hand-written comments. (Box MAC-01)
  - Chapter 1 Manuscript of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 1998 - 2001; 2 typed manuscripts for Chapter 1 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-01)
  - Chapter 1 Manuscript with notations of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 1998 - 2001; Typed manuscript of Chapter 1 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" with hand-written comments and notations. (Box MAC-01)
  - Chapter 2 Manuscript of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, October 23, 2000; Typed manuscript of Chapter 2 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop with hand-written comments by Joe Roesch. (Box MAC-01)
  - Chapter 3 Manuscript with comments of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, June 15, 2001; Typed manuscript for Chapter 3 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" with hand-written comments. (Box MAC-01)
  - Chapter 3 Manuscript of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 2000 - 2001; 2 typed copies of the manuscript to Chapter 3 of the "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-01)
  - Chapter 4 Manuscript of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 2000 - 2001; 2 copies of typed manuscript of Chapter 4 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-01)
  - Chapter 6 Manuscript with notations of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 2001; Typed manuscript for Chapter 6 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" with hand-written comments. (Box MAC-01)
  - Page Proofs of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, August 10, 2004; Typed page proofs for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-01,MAC-08)
  - Revised Manuscript of Introduction to "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 1999; Typed manuscript of the Introduction to "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology with hand-written comments. (Box MAC-02)
  - Manuscript with comments of Introduction to "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 1997; Typed manuscript with hand-written comments of Introduction to "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-02)
  - Table of Contents Manuscript for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 1998 - 2002; Typed manuscript with hand-written comments for the table of contents to "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-02)
  - "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" Chapter 1 Manuscript by James MacKillop, 2000; Typed manuscript to Chapter 1 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-02)
  - "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" Chapter 1 Revised Manuscript by James MacKillop, August 7, 2000; Typed manuscript to chapter 1 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" with handwritten comments. (Box MAC-02)
  - "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" Chapter 2 Manuscripts by James MacKillop, 2000 - 2001; 2 copies of typed manuscript of Chapter 2 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-02)
  - "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" Chapter 2 Manuscript with Comments, September, 2000; Typed manuscript with hand-written comments of Chapter 2 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-02)
  - "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" Chapter 3 Manuscript with Comments, May 6, 2001; Chapter 3 typed manuscript for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop. (MAC-02)
  - "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" Chapter 4 Manuscripts by James MacKillop, 2000 - 2001; 2 typed copies of chapter 4 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop. (Box MAC-02)
  - Chapter 5 Manuscript for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, March 25, 2002; Typed manuscript to Chapter 5 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" with hand-written comments. (Box MAC-02)
  - Chapter 6 Manuscript for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 2002 - 2003; Typed manuscript for Chapter 6 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-02)
  - Chapter 8 Manuscript for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 2002; 2 typed manuscripts for Chapter 8 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" with handwritten comments. (Box MAC-02)
  - Chapter 9 Manuscript for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 2002; 2 typed manuscripts for Chapter 9 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" with handwritten comments. (Box MAC-02)
  - Chapter 10 Manuscript for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 2002 - 2003; Typed manuscript to Chapter 10 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" with hand-written comments. (Box MAC-02)
  - Chapter 10 Manuscript with Revisions for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, December, 2002; Typed manuscript with hand-written comments of Chapter 10 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology.' (Box MAC-02)
  - Chapter 11 Manuscript for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, October 17, 2003; 2 typed manuscripts for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" (Box MAC-02)
  - Chapter 11 Manuscript with Comments for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, October, 2003; Typed manuscript of Chapter 11 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" with hand-written comments. (Box MAC-02)
  - Chapter 12 Manuscript for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, March, 2003; Typed Manuscript to Chapter 12 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" with hand-written comments. (Box MAC-02)
  - Chapter 12 First Draft Manuscript for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 2002 - 2003; Typed manuscript of Chapter 12 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" with handwritten notations. (Box MAC-02)
  - Chapter 14 Manuscripts for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 2003 - 2004; 3 typed manuscripts with hand-written comments of Chapter 14 of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-02)
  - Bibliography Manuscripts for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 1997 - 2004; Typed versions of the bibliography to "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology with hand-written notes. (Box MAC-02)
  - Appendix A (Pronunciation Guide Manuscript) for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 1997 - 2004; Typed manuscript for Appendix A to "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-02)
  - Miscellaneous Appendices and Notes for "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology" by James MacKillop, 1997 - 2004; Typed manuscripts for Appendix C and editing comments for various chapters of "Penguin Guide to Celtic Mythology." (Box MAC-02)
- "Contemporary Irish Cinema" Manuscript Edited by James MacKillop, 1999; Typed manuscript for "Contemporary Irish Cinema" edited by James MacKillop (Box MAC-07)
  - "An Elephant in the Sacristy" Religion in Contemporary Irish Cinema" Manuscript by Pamela Dolan, 1994 - 1995; First draft and final submission of essay, "An Elephant in the Sacristy: Religion in Contemporary Irish Cinema" by Pamela Dolan. Essay is for "Contemporary Irish Cinema", edited by James MacKillop. Includes floppy disk (Box MAC-07)
- "Fionn mac Cumhaill: Celtic Myth in Irish Literature" Manuscript by James MacKillop, December 31, 1985; Typed manuscript with hand-written comments of "Irish Studies" with essay, "Fionn mac Cumhaill" written by James MacKillop. (Box MAC-07)
- Master's Thesis on T.E. Hulme by James MacKillop, 1962; Typed Master's Thesis on T.E. Hulme. Submitted to Wayne State University. Includes hand-written comments, notes and drafts. (Box MAC-10)